<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction on BioDocker Documentation</title>
    <link>http://biodocker.org/docs/tags/introduction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Introduction on BioDocker Documentation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 12:09:52 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://biodocker.org/docs/tags/introduction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What is BioDocker?</title>
      <link>http://biodocker.org/docs/what-is-biodocker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 12:09:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://biodocker.org/docs/what-is-biodocker/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-biodocker&#34;&gt;What is BioDocker?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://biodocker.org&#34;&gt;BioDocker&lt;/a&gt; is a community-driven project that provides the infrastructure and basic guidelines to create, manage and distribute Bioinformatics Docker containers with special focus in Proteomics, Genomics, Transcriptomics and Metabolomics.
BioDocker is based in the popular &lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-docker&#34;&gt;Docker framework&lt;/a&gt;. A revolutionary platform for developers and sysadmins to build, ship, and run applications
anywhere. With Docker you can build an image containing your software and all dependencies and ship it ready to use (see &lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-docker&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;biodocker-goals&#34;&gt;BioDocker Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BioDocker community and project have three major goals:
 &lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A central registry with containers ready to be use: &lt;a href=&#34;biodocker-projects#registry&#34;&gt;The BioDocker Registry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specifications about how to create a BioDocker container/image and infrastructure to deploy them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A complete infrastructure create, share and request docker images from bioinformatics software&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BioDocker/containers&#34;&gt;BioDocker containers&lt;/a&gt; facilitate the usage, integration and reproducibility
of software and algorithms into more comprehensive bioinformatics pipelines. Finally, we presented the guidelines and specifications to create a container, contribute to the group or request a container from the group. Our guidelines and specifications are part of community efforts like Bioboxes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bioboxes&#34;&gt;https://github.com/bioboxes&lt;/a&gt;), open-containers (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/opencontainers&#34;&gt;https://github.com/opencontainers&lt;/a&gt;) or Bioconda (&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconda.github.io/&#34;&gt;https://bioconda.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;) to make installation, addition, evaluation and benchmarking of new algorithms and tools accessible to researchers, minimizing the efforts for installation and configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-docker&#34;&gt;What is Docker?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;medium-6 columns&#34;&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;Docker containers wrap up a piece of software in a complete filesystem that contains everything it needs to run: code, runtime, system tools, system libraries – anything you can install on a server. 
        This guarantees that it will always run the same, regardless of the environment it is running in. 
     &lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;                            
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;medium-6 columns&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
         
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../icons/figure1.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

        &lt;/p&gt;                            
   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>